Guide to the Martha J. Lamb Papers 1756-1892 (Bulk 1876-1892) MS 362
New-York Historical Society
- Series VI. Clippings, 1756-1892, undated (bulk 1876-1883)
  - Clippings re: Lamb in Chicago (Sanitary Fairs, Ladies Relief Society, Lincoln's funeral procession, Ladies Industrial School Association; Lamb, unsigned articles from The Republic; reviews of Lamb's children's books (as "Aunt Mattie"); reviews of Lamb's novel Spicy, 1863-1873, undated (Box 10, Volume [1])
  - Signed and unsigned articles ("Crisp"), probably Lamb; reviews of History of the City of New York, 1870-1876 (Box 10, Volume [2])
  - Lamb, articles; reviews of HCNY and the Christmas Owl; poetry; clippings re: Ladies of Sorosis dinner, (1881), and Goshen, Mass. anniversary, 1875-1882, undated (Box 10, Volume [3])
  - Lamb, signed and unsigned articles Daily Graphic (probably Lamb); reviews of HCNY, 1876-1877 (Box 10, Volume [4])
  - Lamb, signed articles; unsigned articles ("Crisp"), 1876, undated (Box 10, Volume [5])
  - Lamb, articles "Our New York Letter" Bazar, articles for Daily Graphic re: Newport, Saratoga Springs, etc.; signed and unsigned ("Crisp"), 1877, undated (Box 10, Volume [6])
  - Lamb, articles, signed; unsigned, 1878, undated (Box 11, Volume [7])
  - Lamb, articles, unsigned ("Nash Reade"), Undated (Box 11, Volume [8])
  - Lamb (probably), articles, unsigned, Undated (Box 11, Volume [9])
  - Lamb (probably), articles, unsigned "The Rise and Progress of Art", Undated (Box 11, Volume [10])
  - Lamb (probably), articles, unsigned "Hints on Household Decorations", Undated (Box 11, Volume [11])
  - Lamb, articles, "The Broken Pitcher", Undated (Box 11, Volume [12])
  - Lamb, articles, "The Broken Pitcher", Undated (Box 11, Volume [13])
  - Reviews, HCNY, 1876, undated (Box 11, Volume [14])
  - Reviews, HCNY, 1876-1877 (Box 11, Volume [15])
  - Reviews, HCNY; clippings re: Lamb, 1876-1878, undated (Box 11, Volume [16])
  - Reviews, HCNY, 1876-1879, undated (Box 11, Volume [17])
  - Reviews, HCNY, 1877, undated (Box 11, Volume [18])
  - Reviews, HCNY, 1877-1878, undated (Box 11, Volume [19])
  - Reviews, HCNY, 1877-1881, undated (Box 11, Volume [20])
  - Reviews, HCNY, Homes of America, 1877-1882, undated (Box 12, Volume [21])
  - Reviews, HCNY, 1879, undated (Box 12, Volume [22])
  - Reviews, HCNY, 1878-1883 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Reviews and ads for Lamb, various, 1882-1883, undated (Box 12, Volume [23])
  - Loose clippings, various topics, 1874-1881, undated (Box 12, Volume [24])
  - Clippings on various topics inc. women and athletics, NYC, the closing of A.T. Stewart & Co., 1878-1882, undated (Box 12, Volume [25])
  - Clippings on various topics inc. Charles Parkhurst, 1881-1882, undated (Box 12, Volume [26])
  - Clippings on various topics, many NYC, 1882-1883, undated (Box 13, Volume [27])
  - Clippings on various topics (poor condition), 1852, 1888-1890 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    Includes a printed "Map of the City of New York shewing [sic] the original high water line and the location of the different Farms and Estates," lithographed by Geo. Hayward for D. T. Valentine's Manual, 1852.
- Series VII. Huguenot Society of America, 1879-1892, undated
  Lamb was an active member of the Huguenot Society, and was chairman of the Ladies Committee. This series includes letters received by her pertaining to the society, three volumes of committee notebooks and minutes, and various society notes, clippings, genealogies, and ephemera.
  - Lamb, letters received: A - D, 1887-1892 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Lamb, letters received: E - W, 1879-1892 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Lamb, Ladies Committee: notebook, 1887-1888 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Lamb, Ladies Committee: minutes, 1889 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Lamb, Library Committee: minutes, 1888-1891 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Lamb, notes, application, Undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Huguenot Society: genealogies, clippings, copies of administrative documents, notes, 1889-1892, undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Huguenot Society: tickets, calling cards, publications, blank letterhead, 1888-1892, undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Series VIII. Madison Square Presbyterian Church, 1882-1889, undated
  Lamb was involved with the various charitable societies of the Madison Square Presbyterian Church led by the reformer Rev. Charles Parkhurst. She was on the Board of Managers of the Loan Relief Society, and was secretary/ treasurer for the Ladies Association, a group that aimed to unite a number of the church's charitable societies and clubs. This series includes reports for the Loan Relief Society, the Ladies Committee, and other church societies; notes and clippings; and material relating to Mary H. Brown, President of the Loan Relief Society.
  In addition, the Manuscript Department holds one volume of Madison Square Church societies' papers for 1882, including the constitution of the Loan Relief Society. Most of this material is in Lamb's handwriting or is addressed to her; call phrase: BV NYC Churches Presbyterian.
  - Loan Relief Society: committee reports, constitution, notes, 1882-1889, undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Loan Relief Society, Mary H. Brown: letters received, clippings and resolutions on death of ---, notebooks, 1882-1884, undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Ladies Association: society reports, 1889, undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Other clubs / societies: reports, 1889, undated (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Clippings. Re: Charles Parkhurst, Greeley family, 1884, undated (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Series IX. Organizational Material, 1854-1892, undated
  Lamb was a member of many of these historical societies, associations, and clubs. Arranged alphabetically by organization name. Material includes membership certificates, circulars and ephemera pertaining to meetings, correspondence, dues receipts. The larger certificates are housed in the Manuscript Department's oversize cabinets (Ov); call phrase: Y-Lamb, folder *2.
  - American Academy of Political and Social Science: meeting notice, 1891 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science: circulars, forms, tickets, clippings relating to annual meetings, 1880-1887 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - American Historical Association: correspondence, program, 1889-1892 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Charleston Library Society: prospectus, circulars, Undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Clarendon Historical Society; Edinburgh, Scotland: correspondence, membership notices and receipts, certificate of fellowship, 1883-1884 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Daughters of the American Revolution: correspondence, booklets, invitation, 1891, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - General Society of Mechanics and Tradesmen of the City of New York: correspondence, solicitation, invitation, 1889-1892, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Ladies Industrial School Association of Chicago: reports, clippings, constitution, correspondence, notes, insurance policy, 1854-1864, undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Ladies Industrial School Association of Chicago: minutebook, 1854-1861 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Ladies of Sorosis: drafts of toasts and speeches, correspondence, and notes relating to dinner in honor of Lamb, May 12, 1881, 1881, undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - New Century Historical Society: meeting notice, address, 1891-1892 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - New Jersey Historical Society: letters received, etc., 1898-1892 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    Includes Mrs. Frederick H. Pierson's paper, "Mrs. Martha J. Lamb, The Historian," read before the Society, September 28, 1888.
  - New York Academy of Science: receipt for dues, 1887 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - New York Genealogical & Biographical Society: receipt for dues, 1887 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - New-York Historical Society: receipts for dues, notice for Lamb's lecture (1878), fundraising notice, 1878-1892, undated (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - New York Medico-Legal Society: circulars relating to meetings, society members and events, 1890-1892, undated (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Nineteenth Century Club: receipts for dues, 1887, 1889 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Pot Luck Club: picnic invitation and Lamb's regrets, 1881 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Rhode Island Historical Society: invitations, 1885 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Tarrytown Historical Society: meeting notices, 1890-1892 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Tuxedo Club: invitation, 1889 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - X.Y.Z. (literary club): correspondence, 1878 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - General Society of Mechanics and Tradesmen of the City of New York: membership and graduate certificates, Undated (Box Ov, Folder *2)
  - Historical Society of Tennessee: membership certificate, 1888 (Box Ov, Folder *2)
  - New Jersey Historical Society: membership certificate, 1888 (Box Ov, Folder *2)
  - New York Medico-Legal Society: membership certificate, 1889 (Box Ov, Folder *2)
- Series X. Poetry, 1869-1883, undated
  Drafts and proofs of Lamb's poems. Also clippings, drafts, and a pamphlet of poetry by others.
  - Lamb: drafts and proofs (handwritten and printed), 1869-1880, undated (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Others: clippings, drafts, pamphlet, 1880-1883 (Box 15, Folder 8)
- Series XI. Notes, undated
  Includes Lamb's notes regarding her life, publications, historical figures, events, and places. Also notes, not in Lamb's hand, including excerpts from California newspapers the Californian and California Star, 1848 re: Gold Rush, and unidentified notes written on the reverse of wallpaper.
  - Lamb, Notes re: her publications, Undated (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Lamb, Notes re: historical figures, events, places, Undated (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Notes from California newspapers, 1848 (not in Lamb's hand) including letters to ed, articles, ads, poetry, Undated (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Notes, unidentified. Includes fragments of a draft, on reverse of wallpaper (not in Lamb's hand) re: Napoleon's family, Undated (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - "Mrs. Lamb's Study of Herself", 1880 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - "One Corner of Berkshire", [1887?] (Box 17, Folder 14)
    With a Boston Post article, August 8, 1887, describing "Mrs. Martha J. Lamb's Paper on 'My Recollections of One Corner of Massachusetts."
- Series XII. Financial Material, 1882-1891
  Bills and receipts, for professional and personal items.
  - Bills and receipts, 1882-1891 (Box 15, Folder 13)
- Series XIII. Genealogical Material, 1891-1892, undated (bulk undated)
  For Lamb (Reade) plus various families, many New York State. An additional forty genealogies were transferred to the Library in 1957.
  - Lamb: Reade family, Undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - A - J, Undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - K - S, unidentified, 1891-1892, undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Series XIV. Ephemera, 1873-1890, undated
  Includes ads for Lamb's publications, including History of the City of New York (also partial list of subscribers) and Magazine of American History, as well as various ads for hotels, building lots, household items, books, and book accessories. Also included are calling cards, tickets and notices of concerts and lectures, admission tickets to the Fifth Avenue Reading Room and the Tombs, and invitations to graduations and a wedding.
  - Ads for Lamb publications, 1884-1885, undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Ads, 1873-1875,undated (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Calling cards, stationery, Undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Tickets and notices, 1877-1879, undated (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Invitations, 1878, 1890 (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Series XV. Excursion: Marietta, Ohio, 1888
  From July 15 -- 20, 1888, Lamb attended the "National Centennial of the Establishment of Civil Government in the 'Territory North West of the River Ohio' and of the First Settlement thereof under the Ordinance of 1787" at Marietta, Ohio. This series includes programs, correspondence, circulars, publications, clippings, and a B & O R.R. timetable relating to the excursion. Lamb's article about the centennial can be found in the Magazine of American History, Sept., 1888.
  - Programs, correspondence, circulars, publications, timetable, 1888, undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, mostly from Marietta Register, 1888, undated (Box 16, Folder 10)
- Series XVI. Copies of documents, undated
  Includes a copy of the 1776 diary of Dr. James Clitherall, extracts from diaries and letters of Rev. Horace Holley, and an unidentified author's firsthand account of the Chicago fire, 1871. These items do not appear to be Magazine of American History submissions. Lamb's editorial notations can be found on some; their use by her is unclear.
  - Dr. James Clitherall—copy of diary, 1776 (possibly sent to Lamb by G. Woodbridge, Marietta, OH, 1890), Undated (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Rev. Horace Holley—extracts from letters and diary re: Yale, Columbia, Princeton, Undated (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Rev. Horace Holley— copies of letters from New York, 1818, Undated (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Rev. Horace Holley—copy of letter re: visit to Mt. Vernon, 1818, Undated (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Rev. Horace Holley—copies of letters from Edward Everett re: Kean riots of Boston, 1825, Undated (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Copy of document re: Chicago fire, 1871, author unknown, Undated (Box 16, Folder 12)
- Series XVII. Huntington Collection catalog, 1883
  Catalog of the Huntington Collection at the Metropolitan Museum.
  - Huntington Collection, Metropolitan Museum. On microfilm, Misc. reel #46, 1883 (Box 16, Folder 13)
- Series XVIII. Visual Materials, [18]81, 1886, undated
  Includes photographs, glass negatives, sketches, prints, tintypes, printing blocks, and colored prints. Ten items are housed in Oversize cabinets (Ov), call phrase Y-Lamb, folder *3. Printing blocks are housed separately, in Box 18.
  - Cabinet cards, portraits, Lamb (5), Undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Cased photograph, portrait, subject unknown (possibly relative), Undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Sketches, prints, stereographs, photograph of coastal scenes for possible use with Lamb's "American Life Saving Service" (Harper's Feb. 1882) (10 items), [18]81, undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Sketch of New York harbor on tissue paper, Undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Print, map of Europe at the time of Charlemagne (possibly used for MAH), Undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Print, Earl of Beaconsfield (torn into many pieces), Undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Prints, Nash coat of arms (numerous copies), Undated (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Glass negatives, library scene (5), Undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Tintypes (10), sketched portraits and scenes (probably for MAH), Undated (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Printing blocks (5) coats of arms, signatures, Undated (Box 18)
  - Wooden block with sketch, possibly Erie Canal opening celebration, Undated (Box 18)
  - Colored prints (3), owls and blue jays, Undated (Box Ov, Folder *3)
  - Sketches of Louisbourg, Nova Scotia (7), 1886, undated (Box Ov, Folder *3)
- Series XIX. Artifacts, 1881, undated
  Includes souvenir rocks and heather, a key, wax seals, a miniature easel, a book cover, and cardboard. One item housed in Oversize cabinets (Ov), call phrase Y-Lamb, folder *1.
  - Small cache of rocks from Trenton Falls, NY, with notes and wrapping (includes Hoosac Tunnel Route R.R. timetable), 1881,undated (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Sprig of heather, "picked by Mrs Stedman, near Walter Scotts place", Undated (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Small key, "top drawer in cheffonier" [sic], Undated (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Small easel with brush, possibly place-card, inscribed "Mrs. Lamb May 13th 1881." (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Three wax seals, coats of arms, Undated (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Common school book cover, note on cover "Material for October Number", Undated (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Mailing tube, from the Historical Society of Tennessee, Undated (Box 10)
  - Box lid with list of correspondents, Undated (Box Ov, Folder *1)